<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Angels rejoicing for sinners repenting. / Delivered in a sermon by the Right Reverend Father in God, Brian Duppa, now Bishop of Salisbury.</title>
            <author>Duppa, Brian, 1588-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E475_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863864</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863864</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162464</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81856)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 76:E475[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Angels rejoicing for sinners repenting. / Delivered in a sermon by the Right Reverend Father in God, Brian Duppa, now Bishop of Salisbury.</title>
                  <author>Duppa, Brian, 1588-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich: Royston at the Angel in Ivy-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLVIII. [1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 2d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:162464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANGELS REJOICING</hi> FOR SINNERS REPENTING. <hi>DELIVERED</hi> In a <hi>SERMON</hi> by the Right Reverend Father in God, BRIAN DUPPA, now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for RICH: ROYSTON at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Ivy-lane. M.DC.XLVIII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:162464:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:162464:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Angels</hi> rejoicing for Sinners repenting.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>LUKE 15.10.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Likewiſe I ſay unto you, There is joy in the preſence of the Angels of God over one Sinner that repenteth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>An never yet invented more waies to <hi>damn</hi> himſelf, then God hath done to <hi>ſave</hi> him; nor was he ever varied into more ſhapes of <hi>ſinne,</hi> then his Saviour hath been of <hi>mercy:</hi> For as before his incarnation the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had a cloud to uſher them, and God was in that could; <hi>Moſes</hi> had a flame to becken to him, and God was in that flame; <hi>Elias</hi> had a voice to call to him, and God was in that voice: ſo after he was incarnate, when he became one of us <hi>(ſinne alone excepted, which makes us not of him)</hi> as if to have been man alone, was not enough, he ranſacks the whole Inventory of his Creatures, puts on all ſhapes to gaine a Soule: To the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:162464:3"/> Traveller, he calls, <hi>I am the way;</hi> To the benighted, he ſhews, <hi>he is the light;</hi> To the Stranger, he opens himſelf, <hi>I am the dore:</hi> Looke for him among the Plants, you ſhall find him <hi>a vine;</hi> Search for him in the flock, the Baptiſt points him to you, <hi>Behold the Lamb!</hi> or if Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors be but <hi>verball</hi> transfigurings, track him his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables, which are more reall; if you meet there with a Sower, Chriſt is that Sower; if you heare of a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, he is that Bridegroome; if you ſee the <hi>man</hi> that brings back his loſt ſheep in triumph, he is that <hi>man:</hi> or if you find a <hi>woman,</hi> that calls her friends to joy with her, <hi>Rejoice, for I have found the piece which I had loſt;</hi> know that that <hi>piece</hi> is thy Soule, thoſe <hi>friends</hi> are the Angels, he is that <hi>woman</hi> too; For of that Parable, this Text is the morall, the meaning of the Parable, <hi>Likewiſe I ſay unto you, there is joy in the preſence of the Angels of God over one Sinner that repenteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Parables are pictures, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> tells us, but withall, ſuch pictures as have their <hi>velamina,</hi> their ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, their curtaines diaphanous enough for the eye of faith to look through; but not for the eye of unbelief or ignorance. For as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> counſelled a Roman Matron, to keep her young Daughter from reading of the <hi>Canticles, ne anima non intelligens vulneraretur,</hi> leſt the Soule that underſtood not the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> ſenſe, ſhould periſh in the <hi>literall;</hi> or as thoſe Images, which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts call, <hi>Idiotarum libros,</hi> the Lay-mens books, being miſunderſtood doe prove the Fooles Idolatry: ſo theſe Images, (for Parables are but the Images of things) did not ſo much <hi>inſtruct,</hi> as <hi>abuſe</hi> the eyes of them that ſaw them, untill our Saviour drew the curtaine; They had heard of a <hi>ſheep</hi> that had gone aſtray, of a <hi>piece of ſilver</hi> that was loſt: that <hi>both</hi> again were found, that friends
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:162464:3"/> were call'd to rejoice for both. But what this was to them, what ſhare they had either <hi>in this joy</hi> or <hi>that reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,</hi> they had not heard till he that made their eares ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied it to their hearts with an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Likewiſe I ſay unto you,</hi> I that came to heale that which was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to bind up that which was broken, to ſave that which was loſt; I, that have left the ninety nine in the Deſert, all the Angels in heaven (for ſo the Fathers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it) to find out one wanderer; <hi>I ſay unto you,</hi> to <hi>you</hi> Sinners, that come neer to heare me; to <hi>you</hi> Phariſees, that murmure, becauſe theſe Sinners come ſo neer mee; to <hi>you</hi> that know not what the value of a Soule is, what muſick is in the groans, or what beauty is in the teares of a ſad convert, <hi>I ſay to you, there is joy in the preſence of the Angels of God over one Sinner that repenteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The authority of the Speaker muſt win ſome credit to this Argument, for ſo far diſtant is Heaven from Earth, ſo rare the commerce between them, that unleſſe God bring the intelligence himſelf from thence, man will not believe; Let the <hi>Separatiſt</hi> boaſt of his <hi>private ſpirit</hi> that hath <hi>revealed</hi> it, or the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> cite his <hi>infallible Chaire;</hi> every one is not wax enough to take impreſſion at this: But if <hi>our Saviour</hi> ſet his <hi>divine ſeale</hi> on; if we once find his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his <hi>ipſe dico, I ſay unto you,</hi> then let him that hath eares, hear; no Oracle ever ſpake like this, truth, to the truth <hi>incarnate:</hi> Be not therefore troubled either with the <hi>contrariety of paſsions</hi> in theſe words, that <hi>ſorrow ſhould beget joy,</hi> or the <hi>diſparity</hi> of the <hi>perſons,</hi> that <hi>Angels ſhould rejoice for Sinners,</hi> or the <hi>inequality</hi> of the extent, <hi>many Angels</hi> for <hi>one Sinner:</hi> for Chriſt hath ſpoke it, and we are to believe it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>that there is joy,</hi> though we know not what it is.</p>
            <p>Next, there is a <hi>ubi,</hi> a place where, of <hi>this joy,</hi> though it be not here.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:162464:4"/>
            <p>Laſt of all, there is a <hi>quare</hi> too, a why, a reaſon, a cauſe of <hi>this joy,</hi> for <hi>one Sinner that repenteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But firſt of <hi>that joy</hi> it ſelf; for <hi>velut ſolatium erit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian, diſſerere de illo, quo frui non datur,</hi> Sick men may talk of health, and why not I of joy? As in ſorrow the heart is contracted and ſtraitned, ſo in joy the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages are inlarged, the cordiall ſpirits ſcattered, the heart it ſelf runs out, 'tis ſo dilated, which makes <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſay, <hi>that joy is, as it were, the letting of the heart out:</hi> But if they that <hi>feel</hi> no joy cannot define it, nor they that <hi>feel</hi> it, keep it in their hearts; nor he that wants a heart judge of it, who ſhall then reſolve us <hi>what joy is?</hi> or where we ſhal find <hi>a thing</hi> to this <hi>name?</hi> For, examine firſt the <hi>joy of a proud man,</hi> lies it not in the breath of others, a thin ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet of aire which every man hath a key to, but himſelf? Let but them above him agree not to think him great, or wiſe, or noble; Let but his fellow wormes forbeare to honour him; he that holds the plough ſhall not change joies with him. Or look on the joy of the voluptuous: doth not ſorrow often wait ſo cloſe as to tread upon the heels of it? Have you not heard the Epicure cry, <hi>ô his gowt!</hi> even at that time, when he hath been feeding his diſeaſe with riot? Were not the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſtruck with meat between their teeth? and was not <hi>Zimri</hi> ſlaine in the imbraces of his <hi>Cosby?</hi> Beſides, to ſhare in all the good that is under the Sun is at the beſt but <hi>indolence,</hi> a <hi>privation</hi> of grief; it is not joy; or if we wil needs ſtrain higher for a word for it, it is but an acquieſcence, ſaith <hi>Scaliger,</hi> a kind of reſting of the mind, it is not joy: he were a ſtrange Chymiſt you would think, that when a drop of Wine were caſt into the Sea; durſt undertake out of that vaſt Element to extract the ſpirits of that one drop of Wine, and ſay, <hi>here they are:</hi> Nor ſhall I conceive him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162464:4"/> an eaſier Artiſan, that can out of the Sea of his <hi>ordinary hourly</hi> diſcontents, extract this drop of joy, and ſhew it to me. The truth is, we know not <hi>what it is,</hi> becauſe we ſeek not for it <hi>where we ſhould: Copernicus</hi> that thought the Earth moved, and the Heavens ſtood ſtill, was not yet ſo mad as either to look for Trees in Heaven, or for Stars upon the ground; yet we, in our ſearch for <hi>joy,</hi> doe as mad things as this comes to: for what would you imagine if you ſhould ſee a man knock at a Grave-ſtone for a Companion, or go down into a Charnel-houſe to make merry: if you did not pronounce him directly frantick, you would gueſſe ſurely that he had miſtook the place: and the like doe I of you, ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin, Qui quaeritis gaudium in loco non ſuo,</hi> who look for joy either in the honours or pleaſures of this life, or what ever elſe is not the proper ſphere of it.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe there were ſuch a thing on earth as <hi>joy,</hi> that the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> the <hi>Northweſt paſſage,</hi> and that, were found out together; yet there remains another diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition: for, where ſhal we have a <hi>lodging</hi> for it? where a breaſt capable to entertain it? in the heart of the <hi>ſinfull man?</hi> no, God himſelf hath barr'd that dore againſt it: for, <hi>gaudere non eſt impiis,</hi> as we find it denounced in the Propheſie of <hi>Eſay, there is no peace, no joy to the wicked;</hi> they cannot <hi>rejoice,</hi> they may perchance drown their grief in wine, or drive away their diſcontents with company, they may reprieve their ſoules for a time from melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, but the fits of a conſtant Ague, or the flowings of the Tide come not more duly, then it returnes againe; Shifting of the place will not ſerve the turne, unleſſe we can ſhift our ſelves; for, <hi>poſt equitem ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>det atra cura,</hi> like the Rats that followed the German Biſhop, thy ſad thoughts will after thee: Draw the curtains of thy bed,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162464:5"/> yet they wil lie with thee; ſhut the dore of thy cloſet, yet they wil come in unto thee: For the truth is, ſaith S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, Intus est quem fugis,</hi> Every ill man hath his enemy within him, his owne heart calls to him; as his did in the viſion, <hi>ego tibi horum ſum cauſa,</hi> I am the cauſe of all this trouble unto thee: Thou haſt made me <hi>ill,</hi> I will not leave thee <hi>quiet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>No joy then to the wicked:</hi> but ſhall we knock at more <hi>innocent</hi> dores to ſee if <hi>there</hi> it harbours? were the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> in the Old Teſtament acquainted with it? the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles</hi> in the New? or ſhall we inquire of <hi>innocence</hi> it ſelf, the <hi>Saviour</hi> of us all? But he will inquire of us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as he did in the 1. of the <hi>Lam. O all ye that paſſe by,</hi> not was there ever joy, but <hi>was there ever ſorrow like my ſorrow?</hi> But you will ſay perhaps, though he himſelfe were the ſon of ſorrow, yet he bid his followers <hi>joy</hi> in the 5. of <hi>Mat.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>rejoice;</hi> or as if that had been too little, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>be exceeding glad:</hi> True, but it was in their <hi>reproaches:</hi> So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had his <hi>joy,</hi> but it was in his <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions:</hi> the Martyrs had their <hi>joy,</hi> but it was in their <hi>bitter ſufferings.</hi> The few notes they heard of <hi>joy</hi> were but like the breakings of an Eccho, a word or two they heard, but not a ſentence; or like a Ring of Bels in a high wind, they heard ſome imperfect ſounds of it, but they could not heare the Leſſon.</p>
            <p>Yet miſtake me not, I would not have you hang down your heads at this, or becauſe the Earth is not your Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, therefore to make it your Hell: For as gold keeps the name in the leaſe as well as in the wedge, in the coine as in the bullion; or as he that ſees a beame or two ſhine through the crevice of a wall, may ſay he ſees the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine, as well as he that walks abroad; ſo neither are we ſo deſtitute of all comfort, but we may ſay, there is a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:162464:5"/> leafe of joy, the Tinfoile of it here, there are ſome few glimpſes that ſhine in upon us: but for the ful, the ſolid, the jubilating joy, looke for it no longer in this valley of teares: There is joy, but not here; true joy, but not yet: You <hi>that ſow in teares,</hi> be certain <hi>you ſhall reap in joy:</hi> But be as certain to tarry till the harveſt, you muſt ſtay, no remedy, till Heaven be your dwelling, till the Angels be your Partners, incorruption your change, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality your garment: for the earth is not the place, dull fleſh is not the ſubject of it. Find it we ſhall, yet not in the preſence <hi>of Men,</hi> but of <hi>the Angels.</hi> Thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhewn you the negative, where joy is not: My next venture (if it prove not a deſperate one) ſhall be to ſhew you where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the preſence of Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that comes out of a dark Room into the Sunſhine, ſhall be ſure to find his eyes dazeled: What then wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us, whoſe eyes (<hi>Ariſtotle</hi> could ſay) were <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Noctuae ad ſolem?</hi> how ſhall we look on this joy of Angels? ſhall we think of the <hi>place</hi> they live in, or the Company they enjoy, or the Anthems which they ſing, when one Seraphin eccho's to another, or when in a full Quire they ſound together their everlaſting <hi>Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujahs?</hi> or if we can lift up our thoughts ſo high, ſhall we think again, how they ſee the divine face of God? how they joy in that Mirror? how they exult in that bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifick viſion? what fulneſſe? what torrents of pleaſure in ſuch a ſight? ſuch a ſight, ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Auſt. de Spir. &amp; Lit. c.</hi> 55.</note> that if the damned Spirits could but ſee a glimps of it, that very glimps for that time would infuſe ſuch joy into them as to take away the ſenſe of all their paine: ſuch a ſight that the reflected rayes of it, even in this life, gives us that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that Saint <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of, <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>that commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:162464:6"/> with God himſelf.</hi> What then can we conceive of thoſe glorious Creatures, that ſee not God, either by <hi>glimps,</hi> or by <hi>reflexion,</hi> but ſtand under the direct beams, that have a full and eternall fight of him that ſee him <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>face to face,</hi> that heare him even with eare to mouth, that are acquainted with the very whiſpers of the Trinity. But whither am I caried? ſooner ſhall a Sparrow drink up the Sea, or a Moale heave the whole Earth out of the Center, then the heart of man ſwell to that bigneſſe, as to be able to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend his joy.</p>
            <p>Yet as Fathers uſe to acquaint their Heires with their eſtates, before they meane they ſhall poſſeſſe them; ſo, be not angry, ô my God, that we have looked a far off into thoſe joies which with thy Angels we one day ſhall inherit: For though they be of the elder Family, and we like yonger Brothers, weare about us a body of fleſh, for a note of difference, yet this heraldry is not to laſt alwaies; for thou haſt told us, ô my Saviour, that even that diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſhall be took away, that we ſhall be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to the Angels, <hi>aequalitate gratiae,</hi> though not <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas,</hi> in an equality of grace, though not of nature.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhall we offend to inlarge this meditation further, to conceive as ſome of the Fathers did, that as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels fell from ſeverall Hierarchies, ſome from being Seraphins, ſome Cherubins, ſome Thrones, ſome out of higher Seats, ſome out of lower: ſo on that great Day, when God ſhall diſtribute his glory among us, we may opine at leaſt, that into thoſe ſeverall Hierarchies we ſhall be aſſumed: for, among the reſt, <hi>Origen</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently perſwaded, <hi>Quod ſi earum virium eſſet ut vince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Luciferum, Luciferi ſolium in coelo obtineret,</hi> that had
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:162464:6"/> he been of ſtrength enough to have overcome <hi>Lucifer</hi> in temptation that was once the chief of Angels, God would have given him <hi>Lucifers</hi> ſeat in Heaven: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe were this heavenly Court, like the Court of earthly Princes, (where he that is <hi>beneath</hi> bites at the heel of him that is above him; and he that is <hi>above</hi> treads on the mouth that bites him) this might breed rather envy, or hate, or any thing, but joy: But ſo farre are thoſe bleſſed Spirits from envying us for this, that there ſhall be a time when, ſome Men ſhall be higher then ſome Angels, yet even for this <hi>there is joy in the preſence of Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Schoole hath wel diſtinguiſhed a double joy in Angels, either <hi>eſſentiall,</hi> or <hi>accidentall;</hi> their eſſentiall joy conſiſts in the viſion of the Deity, their accidental, in the converſion of us Sinners; the one is alwaies at full Sea, it neither ebbs nor flowes, but the other occaſional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receives either increaſe, or diminution: For as S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> is of the mind, that <hi>Angelus Nomen est officii, non naturae,</hi> to be an Angel is a name of office, not of nature, (in eſſence they are Spirits, but in office only Angels) ſo in that office they accumulate their joy accordingly, as in our protection their ſucceſs is anſwerable to their care: It was well thought on therefore by the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to deſign a Collect in the Liturgie, wherein we pray, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In feſtum Mich:</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that the Angels which alwaies doe God ſervice in Heaven, may by his appointment defend us on Earth:</hi> not that we are to belie their preſence, as that Jeſuite did, who hath bluſhed to print unto the world, that <hi>at the Bohemian o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow, there was viſibly ſeen a troop of Angels to fight on the Emperours part againſt them;</hi> but what Angel joy'd, think you, when that lie was made? yet on the other ſide, we are not to deny them to be our Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:162464:7"/> whether <hi>one</hi> to <hi>one,</hi> or <hi>more</hi> to <hi>one,</hi> ſince their acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall joy doth ordinarily ariſe from thence, even from that imployment.</p>
            <p>Well, but doe the Angels <hi>joy</hi> at the converſion of a Sinner? therefore they <hi>know</hi> it, muſt needs follow (for the <hi>will</hi> moves not till the <hi>underſtanding</hi> ſets it going) <hi>ult: actus intellectus primus eſt voluntatis.</hi> But that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by their evening knowledge; or their morning, as the Schoole diſtinguiſheth, or that therefore in <hi>Verbo tanquam ſpeculo,</hi> in the face of God as in a glaſſe, all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels neceſſarily know the thoughts of all; this will not follow, though all the Jeſuites drive it. No? ſay they, But ſuppoſe there were a glaſſe of cryſtall made ſo large that whatſoever were done in all the corners of the world might be reflected by it; ſhould not he that ſaw that glaſſe diſcern as well all that paſſed under the Sun? juſt ſuch a glaſſe is God unto his Angels; but I doubt the metall of this argument, for a touch or two will break it. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pius à Ponte m.</hi> 1. <hi>p. q.</hi> 12. <hi>r.</hi> 8. <hi>dub.</hi> 15.</note> Firſt, ſome of their own men deny, that the Deity can either <hi>properly,</hi> or by way of Metaphor, be term'd <hi>a Glaſſe,</hi> or next, ſuppoſe it may, yet not <hi>a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Glaſſe,</hi> that repreſents all that is before it: but <hi>a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary,</hi> ſuch a one as ſhews, <hi>non quantum relucet,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> but <hi>quantum voluerit,</hi> not all that ſhines within it: but more or leſſe, when, or how, or to whom he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. God is infinite, whom the Angels ſee, but the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is finite, by which they ſee: Beſides, God knows the inward thoughts, the ſecret glances of the Soul, but the Angels doe not know them: God knows as well what ſhall be, as what is, but the Angels doe not ſo: God knowes the determinate day, reſolved on in his Councels, when the Heavens ſhall be gathered together as a ſcrole, <hi>the Sun ſhall loſe his light, the Graves open,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162464:7"/> and the dead riſe up to judgment, but of that day or howre knows no man elſe, no, not the Angels:</hi> What then is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Jeſuits Cryſtall? if it reflect all, why not this? or if not all, why doe they urge it? But to leave them to their <hi>vitrea fracta:</hi> The Angels know the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of a Sinner; true, but not alwaies, nor all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: They know it, not onely by outward ſignes, but ſometimes by diſcovery of our hearts too. But how? by way of <hi>leave,</hi> by way of <hi>diſpenſation?</hi> For none ever denied, but God imparts to them, <hi>when he</hi> pleaſeth, the converſion of <hi>whom he</hi> pleaſeth: There is knowledge, or elſe there were <hi>no joy</hi> in the preſence of the Angels.</p>
            <p>To conclude this, when God therefore by repentance ſhall call thee to him, when he ſhall performe that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in thee, which Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, is greater then to create a world, to juſtifie thee a ſinner; when he ſhall ſeal thy pardon to thee, with the bloud of his ſon Chriſt Jeſus, doubt not but on that day, God hath revealed this to his Angels, that there is a new joy among them, a full confort in Heaven, that the Holy Ghoſt is buſie <hi>to ſet</hi> new Anthems, the holy Angels as buſie in the ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them.</p>
            <p>And thus we deſcend to the laſt part of the Text, the <hi>[why]</hi> of the joy. <hi>There is joy over one ſinner that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth.</hi> In the which words, we muſt make a new diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery: Firſt, of the object in generall, <hi>a Sinner.</hi> Next of the quality of the Sinner, <hi>the Sinner that repenteth.</hi> Laſt of all, of the indefinite fingularity, <hi>for one Sinner,</hi> implying as much as for <hi>any</hi> one Sinner <hi>that repenteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a ſtrange errour in <hi>Lactantius,</hi> ſo learned a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being deceived by the Tranſlation of the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint, in the ſecond of the ſixt of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> to think that <hi>thoſe ſons of God, that fell in love with the daughters of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162464:8"/> men, becauſe they were faire, were the Angels:</hi> For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other abſurdities, were all the beauty of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens transferr'd into the face of a vitious ſinful Woman, certainly no Angel could have joy in her; and S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> gives the reaſon of it: For their joy extends no further (ſaith he) then the works of God: but <hi>Peccator non eſt inter opera Dei,</hi> a Sinner is no work of God. Look in the firſt Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> you ſhall not find him in the whole Catalogue of his Creatures; as he is <hi>Man,</hi> he is Gods work, true; but as he is <hi>ſinfull man,</hi> he is his own work: ſee him in the pure Robe of originall Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he is Gods work; but look on him in the dreſſings of his owne vanity, he is his owne worke, or if not his owne, I am ſure the Devils: no argument then of joy here, no Ditty for ſuch an Antheme.</p>
            <p>For doe but conſider with thy ſelf ô ſinner, think of it ſeriouſly, the Angels that were by, when God ſtampt his Image on thee, when he waſh'd thee in Baptiſme as clean as the untouch'd ſnow, when he married thee to his ſon Chriſt Jeſus, made thee a temple of his holy Spirit, how can they either <hi>know</hi> or <hi>joy</hi> in thee, when that image is raſed out that innocence polluted, that contract violated, that temple turn'd into a ſink of filth, into a den of Serpents: How wil they look, think you, when God the Father <hi>turnes away his face,</hi> God the Son cries out, <hi>thou hast crucified him again, thou haſt pierced him with thy oaths, ſpit on him with thy luſt, wounded him with thy malice,</hi> when God the Holy Ghoſt <hi>ſhall leave thee, either to a fluctuating, unquiet, or</hi> (which is worſe) <hi>to a ſear'd, a ſtupified conſcience?</hi> which of thoſe bleſſed Spirits can then take joy in thee? ſhall not the ill Angels rather give thee their <hi>Plaudite?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come,</hi> ſay thoſe damned Spirits, <hi>let us ſee this Creature,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:162464:8"/> that was made to fill up our ſeats in Heaven; this Creature that was the Angels joy, and his Gods delight, ſee where he is fallen, how deep, how dangerouſly fallen, how ſtill he lies in his foule ſins, without any motion left, any ſenſe of grace: Ecce</hi> (ſay they) <hi>factus eſt tanquam unus è nobis,</hi> behold he is become like one of us. But <hi>Mentimini mali Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones,</hi> (a devout Father anſwers them) <hi>ye were liers all from the beginning;</hi> ſo are ye now: For, though a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner be fallen, though fallen into the depth of ſinne, he is not become like one of you: For, you fell, <hi>nullo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tante,</hi> without a Tempter, damn'd are you therefore, <hi>nullo reparante,</hi> without a Saviour. But this fall'n ſinner you thus tread upon, <hi>alterius militiâ cecidit, alterius meritis reſurget,</hi> he fell by anothers malice, and ſhall riſe by anothers merit. They were ſome of the black crue that helped to throw him downe; the Son of God, ſhall help him up again: For though ſinne hath been his poyſon, yet repentance may be his antidote; though his ſins have made the Devil ſport, yet his repentance may breed his Angels joy: A ſinner is no good proſpect, but at the ſight of a repentant ſinner Heaven opens all her windows; the Text is warrant enough for ſuch a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>for there is joy in heaven over one ſinner that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not for a ſinner then, but for a repentant ſinner; not for him that hardens himſelf in ſinne, but for the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, melting, bleeding ſinner; but he that would draw repentance to the life, that would make ſuch a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of her, as the Angels might delight in; let him look that he fit her with two faces, on the one ſide a mourning dejected countenance, looking ſadly back on the ſinnes ſhe hath committed, on the other ſide a more cheerfull lively aſpect, looking forwards on new reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162464:9"/> for there is beauty in both, in the ſad as in the cheerfull: God too will look on both, or not at all.</p>
            <p>As for the ſadder look, though <hi>Andreas Vega,</hi> a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Writer, doted ſo much upon it, that he is cenſured by his owne friend <hi>Bellarmine</hi> for maintaining that the ſorrow of the heart for ſinne was of ſo high a value, that he that conceived that ſorrow as he ought, needed no <hi>formall explicite</hi> purpoſe of amendment; though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe this melancholy Frier went too farre, yet let not any therefore deceive himſelf or incline ſo far to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, as to think the way to Heaven is ſtrew'd with Roſes, that he can leap out of the ſtate of ſinne into the favour of his God without ſo much as a ſingle teare or ſigh: No, as it coſt thy Saviour more to redeem thy ſoule, ſo it muſt coſt thee more to apply that redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thee. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> therefore calls Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Laborioſum Baptiſmum,</hi> a laborious, a painfull Baptiſme, a Baptiſme in <hi>Marah,</hi> in the waters of Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs: For we muſt as wel <hi>Flere commiſſa,</hi> as <hi>Flenda non committere,</hi> as well deplore the ill we have done, as not doe againe the ill we have deplored. It is true indeed, what Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>non ſi te excories potes ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facere,</hi> ſhould we weep our ſelves blind, kneele our ſelves cripples, ſhould we flea the skinne from this wretched body of ours, all could not ſatisfie for ſinne: But our joy is, that Chriſt hath already done it; his bloud hath fully ſatisfied for the whole world: yet withall, there lies a Condition on every Sinner, <hi>vel hic flere, vel in futur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a condition that cannot be avoided, either to mourne here, or in the world to come; either to indure now a ſorrow that ſhall <hi>have end,</hi> or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure then a ſorrow that ſhall have <hi>none.</hi> But miſtake me not, I doe not counſell you to a ſullen, continued,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162464:9"/> unintermitted melancholy: but yet pardon me if I would have you throughly ſenſible of your ſinnes when you have done them; for without ſorrow on the earth, I am confident there is no joy in Heaven: There is no Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that repenteth.</p>
            <p>But Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> makes the Queſtion, Which were more bound to God, he that ſhould be preſerved ever innocent, or he that were converted to be truly peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent? and he reſolves it thus, <hi>Innocens majora, poenitens magis debet,</hi> extenſively the innocent owes more, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſively the Penitent: Innocence a Jewell of higher price in the ſubſtance, but Repentance of greater value in the workmanſhip; ſo much of greater value, that in the 7 <hi>verſe</hi> of this <hi>Chapter,</hi> it is proclaimed, <hi>that there is more joy for one repentant Sinner, then for ninety nine that needed no repentance:</hi> but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gives a reaſon for it, when he ſaith, <hi>that where ſinne hath abounded, there grace hath much more abounded.</hi> So that I dare ſay, that God looks neither on the heaven of heavens, nor on the pureſt Seraphin, with ſuch content, ſuch joy, as on a heart well wrought, a heart either carved, or cut, or inlaid with ſorrows, where grief hath been as witty in puniſhing, as pleaſure was before in ſinning; a heart ſtill under the Hammer, and broken into a thouſand pieces: O how buſie is thy Saviour at ſuch a ſight, watching thy ſighs, and numbring thy teares, gathering up the ſeverall pieces of thy broken heart; as if they were ſo many ſcattered Diamonds! how gently he handles them, how curiouſly he reunites them, like a rich watch tooke aſunder to be made the cleaner, and ſet together againe.</p>
            <p>But doth any doubt, when his heart is thus broken, whether this care will be taken for it, or no? is he loath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:162464:10"/> to venture on ſo bitter a Receipt without his Phyſitians oath? why, God will ſweare rather then thy Soule ſhall waver: for, look in the 33 of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> the 11 <hi>verſe, Vivo, inquit Dominus: As I live (ſaith the Lord) I take no delight in the death of a Sinner: Turne ye, turne ye from your evill waies: for why will ye die, ye houſe of Iſrael?</hi> Could any thing be ſpoken more paſſionately? He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts, he exhorts, he expoſtulates; why then doe we doubt? will he not ſave us when we repent, that hath threatned not to ſave us, unleſſe we repent? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyprian. Ser: de Coena.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non patitur contriti cordis Holocauſtum repulſam,</hi> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> had learned ſo much of holy <hi>David,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> 
               <hi>A broken heart, O God, thou wilt not</hi> (or as ſome Tranſlations render it, <hi>thou ſhalt not</hi>) <hi>deſpiſe:</hi> no, we have him ſafe in his own fetters, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled to us in his owne promiſes, if we repent, he <hi>will,</hi> he <hi>muſt</hi> forgive us, for he neither will, nor can deceive us: Let every one of us therefore make that confeſſion as Saint <hi>Austine</hi> did, <hi>O Domine ſi non ſum dignus oculos orando ad coelum levare, at ſum dignus oculos plorando cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care,</hi> though I am not worthy O God to lift up my eyes in praying, yet I am ſure, I am worthy to weare out my eyes in weeping: Though I can plead no innocence, yet I would fain plead repentance; that as my ſins have cauſed the ſorrows of thy Sonne, ſo my ſorrows might cauſe the rejoicing of thy Angels.</p>
            <p>I would go on, but me thinks I heare ſome troubled Soule thus call to me, You tell me heavenly things of this repentance, what power a religious ſorrow hath, that the Lizard doth not gaze more earneſtly on him that ſleeps, nor the Dolphin on the Mariner, then the Angels doe on a weeping Sinner; nay, that God himſelf is pleaſed with ſuch a ſight; that he ſuffers all his anger to be waſhed away in ſuch a ſhowre: <hi>Credo Domine,</hi> I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:162464:10"/> believe this O my God, but wretch as I am, I cannot ſorrow: He that ſhould tell me, that all the joies of heaven were to be bought for one ſingle teare, how could he comfort me, that could not ſhed that teare? <hi>when my eyes are dried up, like the parch'd earth in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, my very heart turn'd Marble, what Moſes ſhall I call to to ſtrike this rock for water?</hi> But ſtay, be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged who ever thou art: the Mother of <hi>Peter Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> it ſeems, was in as great a ſtrait as this, when ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving tranſgreſſed her <hi>vow of continency,</hi> ſhe told her Confeſſor plainly, <hi>that when ſhe ſaw what a Sonne ſhe had brought forth, ſhe could not repent, that ſhe had ſinned in having him:</hi> A hard condition! but her Confeſſor ſadly anſwer'd her, <hi>Dole faltem quod dolere non poſsis,</hi> be ſorry at leaſt that thou canſt not ſorry: and the like muſt I ſay to thee O troubled Sinner; if thou find'ſt but ſo much impreſſion made as to <hi>grieve really,</hi> that thou canſt <hi>not grieve,</hi> know that thou art already come to a degree of that which thou grieveſt thou art not come to; know againe that it is the beginning of that thaw, which at laſt will diſſolve thy very heart to water.</p>
            <p>Six times <hi>Elias</hi> his Servant look'd towards the Sea, before he could ſee any thing; the ſeventh time he ſaw but a Cloud no bigger then his hand, yet that Cloud within few howres covered the Heaven with darkneſſe, and the Earth with raine: juſt ſo may be thy caſe, when thou art praying to thy God as <hi>Calebs</hi> Daughter did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Father, <hi>Dediſti mihi terram aridam, da etiam irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam,</hi> thou haſt hitherto made me the owner of a drie, a barren heart, but give me now ſome ſprings of water, ſome feeling at leaſt, ſome ſorrow for my ſins, though at ſix times bending of thy knees, God doth not grant it thee, though at the ſeventh there appeare but one ſmall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:162464:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:162464:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:162464:12"/> drop ſwimming in thy eyes; yet be not diſcomforted, that drop may prove a ſhowre, or if not ſuddenly, yet in the meane time the Angels begin their joy in that; for, as the leaſt piece of a broken glaſſe may ſerve to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect the face that is before it; ſo from that ſmall drop, that ſpot of ſorrow, there is a reflexion made of thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and as there is a full joy for the totall, the full converſion of a Sinner, ſo there is a proportion, a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of joy for one teare, nay for one deſire of a teare of any <hi>one Sinner that repenteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtay, you muſt remember I told you <hi>repentance</hi> had two faces, not onely a ſad one that look'd back, but a cheerfull, that looks forward on new reſolutions: for, as in diſeaſes, it is not enough to purge, to ſweat, to bleed, unleſſe we keep a ſtricter diet after it: ſo neither are tears, nor ſighes, nor a broken heart ſufficient, unleſſe we forbear to commit again the ſin we ſorrowed for: for, however <hi>Bellarmine</hi> be pleaſed to cenſure <hi>Luther</hi> for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermagnifying that ſaying, <hi>Poenitentia optima, nova vita,</hi> the beſt repentance is a new life; yet in the practiſe of it we ſhall all find, that though contrition may begin our peace with God, yet a new life muſt crowne it; though teares may ſoften the wax for pardon, yet a reſolute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment muſt ſet to the ſeale; you therefore that have recovered out of the contagion of any particular bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſinne, let me beſeech you, as ever you would have the Angels joy for you, not to leane, or liſten, or incline againe to the opportunities, the occaſions that have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed you, to caſt off all inducements to ſinne, to hate even the garment that is ſpotted by the fleſh; for who, having ſcap'd the plague, would not burne the clothes he wore when he was infected? Be not like thoſe plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, unſteady Penitents, who having diſcharged their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:162464:12"/> ſinne this day in the eares of their God; take it up again the next day in the Armes of a Sinner: as if God were bound to ſet no end of pardoning, becauſe they are wilfull to ſet no end of ſinning: <hi>Hoccine poenitere?</hi> is this to repent? can the Angels joy at this? no: as there are no reſts, no ſtops, no pauſes in their intermitted An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themes; ſo they look too there ſhould be no digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, no breakings off in thy repentance. If then any of thy former ſinnes will needs knock unſeaſonably at the dore of thy heart for entrance, anſwer them, as the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles, I have put off my clothes, how ſhould I put them on? I have waſht my feet, how ſhould I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file them? I have put off my ſinnes, why ſhould I reſume them? I am reconcil'd to my God, why ſhould I offend him?</hi> O what triumphs doth he cauſe above that thus anſwers his temptations here! what ſhouts, what peales, what Jubilees of joy, even <hi>for one</hi> ſuch <hi>ſinner that repenteth!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are now come to the laſt particular, <hi>For one Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:</hi> but what for <hi>one?</hi> yes even for <hi>one;</hi> for could it be ſuppoſed, ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine,</hi> that there were but <hi>one</hi> loſt Soule in the whole world, ſuppoſe it were onely thine; yet thy Saviour, thy Jeſus would have come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, he would have ſuffered all that he did ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; thoſe ſcornes, thoſe buffetings, that paſſion, and that death for that one ſoule of thine: If God then would have died for a ſingle Sinner, may it not become the Angels to joy for him, whom their God would die for? Of the ten Leopers whom Chriſt had cured, there was but one turn'd back to thank him, yet there was joy in Heaven even for that one; of the many She-ſinners in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> there was but one <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> that waſh'd her Saviours feet with teares, yet there was joy in Heaven even for that one. Should there want one ſtring
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:162464:13"/> to a lute, the muſick would not be full; or one linke to a chaine, the chaine would be imperfect; or one rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate ſoule to the number of the elect, Heaven would not be ſatisfied: why then doth not every one of us ſtrive to make up that number? how long ſhall God expect for one ſinner to make towards him? when ſhall his holy Angels ſpie ſo much as a promiſing cloud in thine eyes, that thy teares are comming to a ſetled reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in thy heart that thy life is changed? what ſhall I ſay more? Let there be but one among you that ſhall reckon his converſion from this day, God the Father ſhall bleſſe the memory of this day for ever, for he ſhall gaine a ſon: God the Son with his owne bloud ſhall give it a red letter in his Kalender, for he ſhall gaine a Brother: God the Holy Ghoſt ſhall ſanctifie it, for he ſhall gaine a Temple: or if this be not loud enough, all the glorious Angels ſhall at this inſtant ſhout for joy, <hi>even for that one Sinner that repenteth.</hi> Who then would not thus make holy-day in heaven? who would not feaſt the Trinity? or who would not joy the Angels? begin therefore your repentance early: Begin it now, ſince this is the onely way to fill up the number of thoſe Angels that expect you, when in ſtead of having your ſorrows, the burthen of their ſongs, you ſhall become the fellow-ſingers of their Anthemes. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
